CURRICULUM VITAE

Andrzej Hryczuk

Date of birth: 11th December 1983 Address: Place of birth: Warsaw, Poland NCBJ

Nationality: Polish ul. Pasteura 7,

Languages: English (*fluent*), Russian (*good*), 02-093 Warsaw, Poland German (*basic*), Italian (*basic*), ahryczuk.github.io

Polish (native) andrzej.hryczuk@ncbj.gov.pl

Biosketch

Theoretical physicist working on particle cosmology and high energy physics. Research interests include: dark matter, beyond SM phenomenology and QFT at finite temperature. Did extensive research on all these topics and currently focused on evolution of dark matter in the Early Universe.

H-index: 13 (according to **INSPIRE** database).

Work experience

Dec 2018 -	Assistant Professor (Adiunkt), National Centre for Nuclear Research, Warsaw, Poland	
Dec 2015 - Nov 2018	Postdoctoral Fellow, University of Oslo , Norway	
Sep 2015 - Dec 2015	Postdoctoral Fellow, National Centre for Nuclear Research, Warsaw, Poland	
Oct 2012 - Sep 2015	Postdoctoral Fellow, Technische Universität München, Munich, Germany	
Nov 2008 - Oct 2010	Early Stage Researcher, Marie Curie Research Training Network "UniverseNet", SISSA and INFN, Trieste, Italy	
Jul - Oct 2006	Internship at CERN in the OSQAR Collaboration, Geneva, Switzerland Group of Dr. Andrzej Siemko	
Education		
2008 - 2012	Ph.D. Student at SISSA, Trieste, Italy Thesis title: <i>Loop and non-perturbative effects in the dark matter phenomenology</i> Supervisor: Prof. Piero Ullio	
2007 - 2008	Ph.D. Student at the Faculty of Physics, Warsaw University, Poland	
2002 - 2007	M.Sc. Degree in Theoretical Physics with Honours, Warsaw University Thesis title: <i>Axions in Particle Physics and Cosmology</i> Supervisor: Prof. Krzysztof Meissner	
1998 - 2002	Matriculation with Honours, The $14^{ m th}$ Secondary School in Warsaw with the prize of the Mayor of Warsaw-Center District	
Research grants		
Jul 2019-Jul 2022	PI of SONATA grant 2018/31/D/ST2/00813, National Science Centre, Poland Project title: The impact of non-equilibrium and thermal effects on the evolution of Dark Matter in the Early Universe plasma	

Scholarships and Awards

when the standard way of calculating the thermal relic density fails"

Mar 2008 Award for the best M.Sc. thesis at the Faculty of Physics, Warsaw University

Oct 2004 - Oct 2007 Scholarship of the Minister of Science and Higher Education

2nd Oct 2006 Award of the Marshal of the Masovian Voivodeship

18th Dec 2004 Award for the best article published in the periodical Delta in academic year

2002/2003: Niebieski las (Blue Forest), Delta, 351 (2003) 4

 $23^{\rm rd}$ - $30^{\rm th}$ May 2002 $$1^{\rm st}$$ Prize at the $15^{\rm th}$ IYPT, Odessa, Ukraine $22^{\rm nd}$ - $29^{\rm th}$ May 2001 $$3^{\rm rd}$$ Prize at the $14^{\rm th}$ IYPT, Espoo, Finland

Teaching and public outreach

Teaching Selected Topics in Dark Matter, open Lecture Series (UiO, spring 2018)

Classical Mechanics and Special Relativity, Tutor (Warsaw University, spring 2019)

Statistical Physics and Thermodynamics, Master tutor (TUM, 2013/2014) Mathematical Analysis I with Algebra, Tutor (Warsaw University, 2007/2008)

Ph.D Supervision day-to-day co-supervision of Francesco Dighera,

Technische Universität München, 2014-2015

Thesis title: Radiative Corrections in Relic Density Calculations

M.Sc. Supervision co-supervision of August Geelmuyden, Thesis title: On the Prospects of

Microlensing WIMPy Halos, University of Oslo, 2017-2018, Thesis grade: A

co-supervision of Alessio Pizzini, Thesis title: Thermal production of self-interacting

dark matter, University of Oslo, 2017-2018, Thesis grade: C

co-supervision of Ask Markestad, Thesis title: Dark Matter Bound State Formation

for Pseudo-Scalar Mediators, University of Oslo, 2016-2017, Thesis grade: A

Popular talks Interview in the Polish Radio program EUREKA

(23rd Nov 2021)

'Ciemna materia okiem fizyka czastek' (Dark matter seen by a particle physicist),

DM day 2021, (online) (28^{th} Oct 2021)

'Ciemnosc widze, ciemnosc... czyli jak zobaczyc ciemna materie' (How to see the dark

matter),

Maratow wykladowy z Delta, (online) (25th Feb 2021)

'Ciemna strona Wszechświata' (The dark side of the Universe),

Festiwal Nauki, Warsaw, Poland (26th Sep 2020)

'Co kryje sie we wnetrzu czarnej dziury?' (What is inside a black hole?),

Letnie Spotkania z Nauką, Skoczkowo, Poland (13th Jul 2019)

'Entropia i strzałka czasu' (Entropy and the arrow of time),

Letnie Spotkania z Nauką, Skoczkowo, Poland (4th Aug 2018)

'Z czego zbudowany jest Wszechświat?' (What is the Universe Made of?), Letnie Spotkania z Nauką, Skoczkowo, Poland (17th Aug 2013)

'The International Young Physicist Tournament', Polish Seminar on Physics

Teaching, Warsaw, Poland (19th Mar 2003)

Popular papers Piłeczka w szklance wody (Plastic Ball in a Glass of Water)

A. Hryczuk, R. Żak, Delta, 353 (2003) 10

Niebieski las (Blue Forest)

A. Hryczuk, R. Żak, Delta, 351 (2003) 4

O unoszeniu sie ciał na wodzie (On Floating of Bodies)

A. Hryczuk, R. Żak, Delta, 347 (2003) 11

Inv	rited	l Ta	lks

25 th Nov 2021	'Freeze-in of Dark Matter: recent developments', invited seminar at University of Warsaw, Warsaw, Poland (online)
23 rd Sep 2021	'Dark Matter and the H_0 tension', invited parallel talk at the Polish Physicists' Summit (Zjazd Fizykow Polskich), Bydgoszcz, Poland (online)
$9^{ m th}$ Jan 2020	Heavy WIMPs: status and future prospects, invited plenary talk at Rencontres du Vietnam, Quy Nhon,
24 th Oct 2019	'Dark Matter at the TeV frontier', invited seminar at University of Warsaw, Warsaw, Poland
14 th Sep 2019	'Non-equilibrium effects in the evolution of Dark Matter', invited parallel talk at the Polish Physicists' Summit (Zjazd Fizykow Polskich), Cracow, Poland
18 th Mar 2019	'Non-equilibrium effects in the evolution of Dark Matter', invited joint CPT/CPPM seminar, Marseille, France
9 th Nov 2018	'Particle Dark Matter at a Crossroads', invited colloquium at Institute of Theoretical Astrophysics, Oslo, Norway
22 th Dec 2017	'Kinetic Decoupling of Dark Matter and its impact on the Relic Density', invited seminar at University of Warsaw, Warsaw, Poland
7 th Nov 2017	'(More) exceptions in the calculations of relic abundances', invited seminar at LPTHE, Paris, France
28 th Sep 2016	'Relic Density at NLO: IR finteness', invited talk at "Rethinking Quantum Field Theory" workshop, DESY, Hamburg, Germany

Contributing talks and presentations

28 th July 2021	'DRAKE: Dark matter relic abundance beyond kinetic equilibrium', EPS-HEP conference, DESY, Germany (online)
19 th May 2021	'Dark matter relic abundance beyond kinetic equilibrium', PPC workshop, University of Oklahoma (online)
4 th Dec 2020	'Self-interacting DM and the H_0 tension', SAFIR DM workshop, Sao Paolo, Brazil (online)
28 th Aug 2018	'Early Kinetic Decoupling of DM: when the standard way of calculating the thermal relic density fails', COSMO 2018, Deajeon, South Korea
$14^{ m th}$ Mar 2018	'Dark Matter Relic Density: revisited', Rencontres de Moriond, La Thuille, Italy
29 th Jul 2016	'Relic Density at NLO: thermal corrections', The Dark Side of the Universe, Bergen, Norway
20^{th} Jul 2016	'Neutralino dark matter at TeV scale revisited', IDM, Sheffield, UK
$4^{ m th}$ Jun 2016	'Spectral features in the Mev-gap', Warsaw Workshop on Non-Standard DM, Poland
27 th Jan 2016	'Two (more) exceptions in the calculations of relic abundances', Theory Seminar, University of Oslo, Norway
9 th Sep 2015	'The relic density of heavy neutralinos', COSMO 2015, Warsaw, Poland
26 th Jun 2014	'Relic density at NLO: the thermal IR divergence', PASCOS 2014, Warsaw, Poland

10 th Oct 2013	'The indirect detection signals of Wino dark matter', Workshop on the Future of Dark Mater Astro-Particle Physics: Insights and Perspectives, ICTP, Trieste, Italy (poster)
5 th Mar 2013	'The indirect detection signals of Wino dark matter', Astrofizyka Cząstek w Polsce, Jagiellonian University, Kraków, Poland (poster)
20^{th} Feb 2013	'Sommerfeld enhancement', HAP Dark Matter 2013, Münster University, Germany
30 th May 2012	'Electroweak and Sommerfeld corrections to the Wino DM annihilation', PLANCK 2012, University of Warsaw, Poland
$14^{ m th}$ Sep 2010	'Sommerfeld enhancements in the MSSM', 4th UniverseNet School, Lecce, Italy
23 rd Jun 2010	'The Sommerfeld enhancements in the MSSM', FA51 Group Meeting, Laboratori Nazionali di Frascati, Frascati, Italy

Others

- Referee for: Physical Review Letters, Physical Review D, Physics Letters B, JCAP, European Physical Journal C, Europhysics Letters
- Scientific secretary for the Particle Astrophysics in Poland conference, 20-21 May 2019, Warsaw
- Organization of the *Dark Matter Day* 2021 in Poland outreach event, 28 October 2021

Computer skills

- Programming: C/C++, FORTRAN, Wolfram Language (Mathematica)
- Web: Html, CSS, basics of PHP Webmaster of the SISSA High Energy Sector webpage (Oct 2010 Nov 2011) and of the Ph.D. Students' Council at Faculty of Physics, Warsaw University (Feb Sep 2008)

List of Publications

Andrzej Hryczuk

The publication culture in the field does not distinguish the first or corresponding authors - the author list is alphabetical and journals do not differentiate authors' contributions. Below I divide the publications into main author papers and contributing author papers. Main authorship entails important contributions to all aspects of the project and publication preparation, where it is understood that often there can be more than one main author.

Bibliometrics from inSPIRE:

Total number of citations: 813

H-index: 13

Bibliometrics from Web of Science: Total number of citations: 555

H-index: 11

Main Author Publications

[1] Dark matter freeze-in from semi-production

A. Hryczuk, M. Laletin JHEP 06 (2021) 026 [arXiv:2104.05684 [hep-ph]]

[2] DRAKE: Dark Matter Relic Abundance beyond Kinetic Equilibrium

T. Binder, T. Bringmann, M. Gustafsson, A. Hryczuk Eur. Phys. J. C 81, 577 (2021) [arXiv:2103.01944 [hep-ph]]

[3] Self-interacting dark matter from late decays and the H_0 tension

A. Hryczuk, K. Jodlowski Phys.Rev.D 102 (2020) 4 [arXiv:2006.16139 [hep-ph]]

[4] Impact of uncertainties in the halo velocity profile on direct detection of sub-GeV dark matter

A. Hryczuk, K. Karukes, L. Roszkowski, M. Talia JHEP **2020** (2020) 081 [arXiv:2001.09156 [hep-ph]]

[5] Forbidden frozen-in dark matter

L. Darme, A. Hryczuk, D. Karamitros, L. Roszkowski JHEP **1911** (2019) 159 [arXiv:1908.05685 [hep-ph]]

- [6] Testing dark matter with Cherenkov light prospects of H.E.S.S. and CTA for exploring minimal supersymmetry A. Hryczuk, K. Jodlowski, E. Moulin, L. Rinchiuso, L. Roszkowski, E. M. Sessolo, S. Trojanowski JHEP **1910** (2019) 043 [arXiv:1905.00315 [hep-ph]]
- [7] Improved bounds on \mathbb{Z}_3 singlet dark matter

A. Hektor, A. Hryczuk, K. Kannike JHEP **1903** (2019) 204 [arXiv:1901.08074 [hep-ph]]

[8] Early kinetic decoupling of dark matter: when the standard way of calculating the thermal relic density fails T. Binder, T. Bringmann, M. Gustafsson, A. Hryczuk Phys.Rev D96 (2017) no.11 115010 [arXiv:1706.07433 [hep-ph]]

[9] The last refuge of mixed wino-Higgsino dark matter
M. Beneke, A. Bharucha, A. Hryczuk, S. Recksiegel, P. Ruiz-Femenia
JHEP 1701 (2017) 002 [arXiv:1611.00804 [hep-ph]]

[10] Novel Spectral Features in MeV Gamma Rays from Dark Matter T. Bringmann, A. Galea, A. Hryczuk, Ch. Weniger Phys.Rev D95 (2017) no.4 043002 [arXiv:1610.04613 [hep-ph]]

[11] Finite-temperature modification of heavy particle decay and dark matter annihilation M. Beneke, F. Dighera, A. Hryczuk JHEP **1609** (2016) 031 [arXiv:1607.03910 [hep-ph]]

[12] *Relic density of wino-like dark matter in the MSSM*M. Beneke, A. Bharucha, F. Dighera, C. Hellmann, A. Hryczuk, S. Recksiegel, P. Ruiz-Femenia JHEP **1603** (2016) 119 [arXiv:1601.04718 [hep-ph]]

[13] *Relic density computations at NLO: infrared finiteness and thermal correction* M. Beneke, F. Dighera, A. Hryczuk JHEP **1410** (2014) 045 [arXiv:1409.3049 [hep-ph]]

[14] Indirect Detection Analysis: Wino Dark Matter Case Study
I. Cholis, A. Hryczuk, R. Iengo, P. Ullio and M. Tavakoli
JCAP **1407** (2014) 031 [arXiv:1401.6212 [astro-ph.HE]]

[15] *The one-loop and Sommerfeld electroweak corrections to the Wino dark matter annihilation* A. Hryczuk, R. Iengo JHEP **1201** (2012) 163, Erratum-ibid. 1206 (2012) 137 [arXiv:1111.2916 [hep-ph]]

[16] *The Sommerfeld enhancement for scalar particles and application to sfermion co-annihilation regions* A. Hryczuk Phys. Lett. **B699** (2011) 271-275, [arXiv:1102.4295 [hep-ph]]

[17] *Relic densities including Sommerfeld enhancements in the MSSM* A. Hryczuk, R. Iengo, P. Ullio JHEP **1103** (2011) 069, [arXiv:1010.2172 [hep-ph]]

Contributing Author Publications & Proceedings

[C1] Non-equilibrium Effects in the Evolution of Dark MatterA. HryczukActa Phys. Pol. B Proc. Suppl. 13, 725 (2020)

[C2] Forbidden Freeze-inL. Darme, A. Hryczuk, D. Karamitros, L. RoszkowskiActa Phys. Pol. B Proc. Suppl. 13, 733 (2020)

[C3] Phase transitions and gravitational waves in models of $\mathbb{Z}_{\mathbb{N}}$ scalar dark matter N. Benincasa, K. Kannike, A. Hektor, A. Hryczuk, K. Loos PoS EPS-HEP2019 (2020) 089

[C4] Dark Matter Relic Density Revisited: The Case For Early Kinetic Decoupling T. Binder, T. Bringmann, M. Gustafsson, A. Hryczuk Contribution to Moriond EW 2018 [arXiv:1805.00526 [hep-ph]] [C5] Science with e-ASTROGAM (A space mission for MeV-GeV gamma-ray astrophysics)
A. Hryczuk in A. De Angelis et al.
JHEAp 19 (2018) 1-106 [arXiv:1711.01265 [astro-ph.HE]]

[C6] Optical Search for QED Vacuum Magnetic Birefringence, Axions and Photon Regeneration A. Hryczuk in P. Pugnat et al. CERN-SPSC-2006-035 (Nov 2006)